A Register of the Robert A. Fearey Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Robert A. Fearey Papers
1939-2004
2005C5
Fearey, Robert A.
7 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box (3.2 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Speeches and writings, correspondence, interviews, reports, memoranda, press releases, printed matter, and photographs, relating to American-Japanese relations before and after World War II, American occupation policy in postwar Japan, the treaty of peace between Japan and the United States in 1951, and the American administration of the Ryukyu Islands.
Administrative Information
Access
The collection is open for research
Access to audiovisual materials requires at least two weeks advance notice. Audiovisual materials include sound recordings, video recordings, and motion picture film. Hoover staff will determine whether use copies of the materials requested can be made available. Some materials may not be accessible even with advance notice. Please contact the Hoover Institution Archives Audiovisual Specialist for further information.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2004
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternative Forms of Material Available
Selected writings and other documentation about Robert A. Fearey found in the collection may also be found in electronic format on the website of his son, Seth Fearey, at: http://www.connectedcommunities.net/robertfearey/
Biography Note
1918 July 4 Born, New York City
1937-1941 Attended Harvard University
1941-1942 Private secretary to Ambassador Joseph C. Grew in Tokyo and after repatriation, in Washington D.C.
1942-1945 Japanese and Far East post-war planning in the Department of State, Washington D.C.
1945-1946 Special assistant to Ambassador George Atcheson, U.S. political adviser to General MacArthur, in Tokyo
1946-1950 Japanese desk officer in the Department of State
1950 Special assistant to the director of the Office of Northeast Asian Affairs, detailed to Japanese peace treaty planning
1950-1951 Assistant to Ambassador John Foster Dulles in negotiation of Japanese peace treaty in Washington, Tokyo, London; technical adviser at the Japanese Peace Conference in San Francisco
1952 Staff of U.S. representative on NATO Council of Deputies, London
1952-1956 Member of U.S. delegation to NATO, Paris
1956-1957 Officer in charge of North Atlantic Treaty Economic and Military Assistance Affairs, Department of State
1957-1958 NATO adviser, Department of State
1958-1959 Student, National War College
1959-1961 Chief, Political-Military Affairs Branch, American Embassy, Tokyo, concerned with negotiation of U.S.-Japan security treaty
1961-1962 Officer in charge of Japanese affairs, Department of State
1963-1966 Deputy director, and then director, for East Asian affairs, responsible for Japan, Republic of Korea, Republic of China, Department of State
1966-1969 Political adviser, Department of State Commander in Chief Pacific (CINCPAC)
1969-1972 U.S. Civil Administrator of the Ryukyu Islands (USCAR)in Okinawa, the last U.S. civil administrator before reversion to Japan
1972-1975 Chairman, Department of International Relations and Area Studies, National War College
1975-1977 Special assistant to the secretary of state and coordinator for combating terrorism
1977-1978 Consultant to Agency for International Development
1978-1979 Special assistant to coordinator of population affairs, Department of State
1979-1997 Special assistant to the president of Population Action International, Washington, D.C.
2004 February 28 Died
Scope and Content of Collection
The Robert A. Fearey papers document Fearey's role as an American statesman and diplomatic official in Japan and the Far East. A majority of the documentation relates to American-Japanese relations before and after World War II, American occupation policy in postwar Japan, the treaty of peace between Japan and the United States in 1951, and American administration of the Ryukyu Islands.
The bulk of the collection documents the positions held by Fearey in the U.S. Department of State and Foreign Service. Of particular note is information in the Biographical File about the United States Embassy in Tokyo in 1940-1942, when Fearey worked as the personal secretary to Ambassador Joseph C. Grew. Documents include speech texts, memos, social programs, photographs, and a log book that documents the internment of the Embassy's staff from December 16, 1941, to June 17, 1942. This period is also discussed in Fearey's My Year with Ambassador Joseph C. Grew, found in the Writings and Speeches series.
Additional information in the Biographical File documents Fearey's role from 1969-1970 as the last U.S. Civil Administrator of the Ryukyu Islands (Okinawa) before reversion of the area to Japan. Files, news releases, photographs, and photograph albums describe the time.
Correspondence includes letters of both a business and personal nature, arranged by name of correspondent. Additional correspondence may be found in the Writings and Speeches series.
Documentation in the Writings and Speeches includes drafts, versions, and final published articles as well as correspondence and other materials relating to these articles. Some articles were published in multiple periodicals. The series also contains notes, drafts and correspondence regarding speeches and interviews.
Collected Research consists of documents that are of similar subject content to the materials in the Writings and Speeches series, collected by Fearey as background research or collected due to use of Fearey's own interviews in others' writings.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into four series: Biographical File, Correspondence, Writings and Speeches, and Collected Research.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in Stanford University's online catalog.
Subjects
United States. Dept. of State.; World War, 1939-1945--Diplomatic history.; United States--Foreign relations--Japan.; Japan--Foreign relations--United States.; Japan--History--Allied occupation, 1945-1952.; Ryukyu Islands.; Diplomats--United States.
Container List
- Biographical File, 1939-2004.
  Includes a curriculum vitae, commissions, assignments, evaluations, commendations, awards, and personal documents, as well as information on Fearey's wife, Mrs. Shirley Fearey. Career files contain documentation on most positions Fearey held in government or private business, including his time in the Tokyo Embassy during 1940-1942 and his work as the last U.S. Civil Administrator of the Ryukyu Islands in Okinawa. Arranged in two groups, general and career files.
  - General
    - Curriculum vitae, 2002, undated (Folder 1: 1)
    - Diplomas and commissions, 1939-1969 (Folder 1: 2)
    - Assignment notices, 1943-1974 (Folder 1: 3)
    - Foreign Service and Department of State evaluations, 1951-1977 (Folder 1: 4)
    - Commendations, 1941-2002 (Folder 1: 5)
    - Foreign Service promotions congratulations
      - 1960 (Folder 1: 6)
      - 1966 (Folder 1: 7)
    - Decoration for distinguished civilian service, Civil Administration of Okinawa, 1972 (Folder 1: 8)
    - Retirement reception from Population Action International, 1997 (Folder 1: 9)
    - Mrs. Shirley Fearey, 2004 (Folder 1: 10)
    - Clippings, 1942-1981, undated (Folder 1: 11)
    - "Nuggets of Expression" clippings, undated (Folder 1: 12)
  - Career Files
    - Private secretary to Ambassador Joseph C. Grew, Tokyo, 1941-1942, undated (Folder 1: 13-14)
    - "O.D. book" log book, American Embassy, Tokyo, 1941 December 16 - 1942 June 17 (Folder 1: 15)
    - Tokyo embassy and Ambassador Joseph C. Grew photographs, 1941, undated (Folder 1: 16)
    - Japanese post war planning, 1943-1946 (Folder 1: 17)
    - Japanese post war agrarian reform, 1945 (Box-folder 2: 1)
    - Harvard Board of Overseers Committee on Far Eastern Civilizations, 1947-1949 (Folder 2: 2)
    - National War College, 1958-1974 (Folder 2: 3)
    - Japan-Dulles Peace Treaty, January 1951 (Folder 2: 4)
    - Japan peace treaty negotiations, September 1951 (Folder 2: 5-6)
    - Political Adviser, Department of State Commander in Chief Pacific, Honolulu, Hawaii, 1967-1968 (Folder 2: 7)
    - U.S. Civil Administrator of the Ryukyu Islands (Okinawa), 1969-1972
      - Appointment, 1969 (Folder 2: 8)
      - Directory chart, 1971 (Folder 2: 9)
      - News releases, 1969-1972 (Folder 2: 10)
      - Interviews, reminiscences, 1972-1982 (Folder 2: 11)
      - Photographs, 1969-1972 (Folder 2: 12)
      - Official captioned photographs, 1969 (Folder 2: 13)
      - Photograph albums, 1969-1972 (Box 8)
      - Clippings, 1969-1972 (Box-folder 2: 14)
    - Special Assistant to Secretary of State Kissinger and Coordinator for Combating Terrorism, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 3: 1)
    - Conference on International Terrorism photographs, 1976 (Folder 3: 2)
    - Commemorative events for the 20th anniversary of the reversion of Okinawa, Tokyo, 1992 (Folder 3: 3)
    - Events celebrating the 50th anniversary of the Japan Peace Treaty, San Francisco, 2001 (Folder 3: 4)
    - San Francisco and the 1951 U.S.-Japan Peace Treaty Conference, by Uldis Kruze, 2001 (Folder 3: 5)
- Correspondence, 1950-2004.
  Contains correspondence of both a business and personal nature. Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent. Additional correspondence relating to his writings, speeches, and interviews may be found in Writings and Speeches, while correspondence relating to Fearey's career may be found in the Biographical File.
  - General, 1950-2004 (Folder 3: 6-7)
  - Acheson, David C., 1993-2001 (Folder 3: 8)
  - Bix, Herbert, 2000-2003 (Folder 3: 9)
  - Dore, R.P., 1958 (Folder 3: 10)
  - Eldridge, Robert D., 2001-2002 (Folder 3: 11)
  - Foster, Clifton, 2001 (Folder 3: 12)
  - Grove, Brandon, 2003 (Folder 3: 13)
  - Janssens, Rudolf, 1994-1995 (Folder 3: 14)
  - Maechling, Charles, 1979-2000 (Folder 3: 15)
  - Ota, Masahide, 1984 (Folder 3: 16)
  - Nakasone, Yasuhiro, 1988-2001. (Folder 3: 17)
    Includes photographs
  - Schwartzberg, Steven, 1990, 1993 (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - Smith-Hutton, Henri, undated (Folder 4: 2)
  - Sullivan and Cromwell, 2000-2001 (Folder 4: 3)
  - Taniguchi, Tomoniko, 2001 (Folder 4: 4)
  - United States-Japan Foundation, 2003 (Folder 4: 5)
- Writings and Speeches, 1941-2003.
  Consists of Fearey's writings, speeches, and interviews. Arranged chronologically
  - Eyewitness to the U.S.-Japan Peace Treaty Conference, An Interview with Robert Fearey, undated (Folder 4: 6)
    (VHS videocassette, 55 minutes)
  - Commodity Exchanges (Harvard honor's thesis), 1941 (Folder 4: 7)
  - "Report," Foreign Relations 1945, volume VI, Japan (Folder 4: 8)
  - The Occupation of Japan: Second Phase, 1948-1950
    Macmillan Company,
    - Incomplete photocopies, 1950 (Folder 4: 9)
    - Correspondence, 1951 (Folder 4: 10)
    - Newspaper reviews, 1951 (Folder 4: 11)
  - "Japan Peace Treaty", speech, Groton School, 1952 (Folder 4: 12)
  - "The Concept of Responsibility"
    - Journal of Criminal Law, Criminology, and Police Science, 1954 June (Folder 4: 13)
    - Related research, 1951-2003 (Folder 4: 14)
    - Related research, 2003-2004 (Box-folder 5: 1)
    - Versions, 2001-2002 (Folder 5: 2-3)
    - Correspondence, 1998-2003 (Folder 5: 4-7)
    - Related clippings, 1986-2001 (Folder 5: 8)
  - U.S. versus U.S.S.R.: Ideologies in Conflict, Public Affairs Press, 1960 (Folder 5: 9)
  - "Terrorism", speech, Federal Bar Association, 1975 (Folder 5: 10)
  - Silent Explosion, with Marshall Green, Department of State Bulletin, 1978 (Folder 5: 11)
  - Kyodo News Service interview, 1982 (Folder 5: 12)
  - Agriculture Policy Research Committee, Inc. interview, 1984 (Folder 5: 13)
  - Asahi Broadcasting Corp. interview, 1984 (Folder 5: 14)
  - "Japan: Constitutional Revision" 1987 interview, 1946-2003 (Folder 5: 15)
  - John Foster Dulles Centennial Conference: The Challenge of Leadership in Foreign Affairs, speech, 1988 (Box-folder 6: 1)
  - Gohda, Kimikazu, interview, 1989 (Folder 6: 2)
  - NHK Japan Broadcasting Corporation, interview on the treaty of mutual cooperation and security, 1990 (Folder 6: 3)
  - "My Year with Ambassador Joseph C. Grew,", 1991-2004
    - Foreign Affairs Oral History Collection, Association for Diplomatic Studies, Arlington, VA, 1991. Self interviewed written history (Folder 6: 4)
    - Journal of American-East Asian Relations, Spring 1992 (Folder 6: 5)
    - Self Published by Seth G. Fearey, 2004 (Folder 6: 6)
    - Research materials, 1941 (Folder 6: 7)
  - "Tokyo 1941: Diplomacy's Final Round" Foreign Service Journal, December 1991. Secondary publication: Foreign Service Reader: Selected Articles, 1997 (Folder 6: 8)
  - NHK Japan Broadcasting Corporation interview on U.S.-Japan relations, 1992 (Folder 6: 9)
  - Okinawa speech, 1992 (Folder 6: 10)
  - "Might the Pacific War Have Been Avoided?", 1994-2003
    - Groton School Quarterly, May 1994 (Folder 6: 11)
    - Bungei Shunju (Japanese Translation), November 2001 (Folder 6: 12)
    - http://connectedcommunities.net, 2002 (Folder 6: 13)
    - Correspondence, 1978-2003 (Folder 6: 14)
  - Documentary Workshop, Inc. interviews, Osaka Japan, 1995-1996 (Box-folder 7: 1)
  - NHK Japan Broadcasting Corporation interview on U.S.-Japan relations, 1999-2002 (Folder 7: 2)
  - National association of Japan-American societies, interview for the 50th anniversary of the San Francisco treaty, 2001 (Folder 7: 3)
  - Kruze, Uldis interview, 2003 (Folder 7: 4)
  - MBC Korean TV Station interview, 2003 (Folder 7: 5)
- Collected Research, 1939-1998.
  consists of materials by other authors similar to his own work. Arranged chronologically.
  - Clippings, 1939-1975 (Folder 7: 6)
  - Ambassador Joseph C. Grew: A Tribute, by J. Graham Parsons, undated (Folder 7: 7)
  - Naughty Marietta: Ni Ni Koko, by Jeff Parsons, undated. (Folder 7: 8)
    Draft
  - Tokyo 1941: Parts I and II, by John K. Emmerson, Foreign Service Journal, 1976 (Folder 7: 9)
  - The Occupation of Japan, Economic Policy and Reform, Proceedings of a symposium sponsored by the MacArthur Memorial, ed. Lawrence H. Redford, 1980 (Folder 7: 10)
  - Okinawan Reversion Story: War, Peace, Occupation, Reversion, 1945-1972, by Gordon Warner, published by Gordon Warner, 1995 (Folder 7: 11)
  - Okinawa in Postwar U.S.-Japan Relations, 1945-1952: The origins of the Bilateral Okinawa Problem, by Robert D. Eldridge, dissertation, Kobe University, 1998 (Folder 7: 12-13)